个人原创 严禁剽窃
翻译/时间轴/校对:JokerChou
个人原创 转载压制请保留译者信息
真实故事改编
血糖正常
blood glucose fine.
肝肾功能正常
Liver function, kidney function,normal
血小板数量正常
Platelet count normal,
血红蛋白正常
hemoglobin levels normal,
血压 131/92
blood pressure, 131 over 92
不高吗
Isn't that high?
体重正常
Weight fine
腰围最好再少一两公分
could do with losing a centimetre or two of your waist.
大便样本未定
Stool sample outstanding
不 意思是你还没提供给我们
No, that means you haven't provided one yet.
噢 是的 我想起来了
Oh yes. No, I'd remember
觉得不难闻是吗
Did you think it didn't stink or something?
你身体没什么问题 马丁
There's basically nothing wrong with you Martin.
你太太告诉我
And your wife tells me
你担心自己有点抑郁
you think you're mildly depressed
我被解雇了 失业中
I got a sack. I'm unemployed.
可那不是你的错 不是吗
But it wasn't your fault, was it?
这大概就是我抑郁的原因
That's probably why I'm depressed -
为我压根就没说过的话被解雇
I was sacked for saying something I didn't say!
试试跑步
Try running
根本就是子虚乌有
I said the exact opposite of what I was sacked for!
你现在在忙些什么
What are you working on at the moment?
考虑写一本书
I was thinking of writing a book.
很好 关于什么的
That's good. What about?
俄罗斯历史
Russian history.
试着跑步吧
Try running
运输部长斯蒂芬·拜尔斯
The Whitehall feud between the transport secretary Stephen Byers
与前任新闻秘书马丁·西克史密斯之间的争执 继续发酵
and the former press secretary Martin Sixsmith continues to grow.
西克史密斯先生已经就这一纠纷发表自己的观点
Mr Sixsmith has been putting his side of the argument.
唐宁街形容这起事件为一场肥皂剧
Downing Street described the affair as a soap opera.
没有迹象表明西克史密斯先生今天在家中
There was no sign of Mr Sixsmith at his home today
在私下里试图证明自己的清白 一周之后
after a week trying to clear his name in private
他如今要把事情公开
He's now gone public
他告诉星期日时报
He told The Sunday Times
政府的高级官员向他表示支持
the senior figures in government had offered him their support
他们向我担保 他们承认
They assured me they accepted
无疑有针对我的不公正行为
there was no suspicion of misconduct against me
我当时非常震惊
I was therefore amazed
他们单方面解雇我
they had unilaterally resigned me
我想就马丁·西克史密斯先生离职一事作出声明
I'd like to make a statment regarding the circumstances of Mardin Sixsmith's resignation
问题是 布莱尔先生打算袖手旁观多久
The quesion is how long Mr Blair stand by his man and not himself be damaged
毫无疑问这又是一个令政府尴尬的事件
There's no doubt that there's been yet another embarrassment of the government
他们不仅要吞下这个奇耻大辱
They've not only had to eat fantastic quantities of humble pie.
而且这种屈辱还带有卑躬屈膝的意味
indeed humble pie I would say, with a side order of grovel sauce
你在这儿
There you are.
太尴尬了
That was embarrassing.
托尼神父问我你去哪儿了
Father Tunney asked me where you disappeared.
嗯 我不相信上帝 他应该能看出来
Well, I don't believe in god.I think he can tell.
好吧
Come on
我很担心你 马丁
I'm worried about you.Martin.
我跑步了
I did that.
希望如此 你需要回去工作
I wish you had.You need to get back to work.
那本俄罗斯历史的书怎样了
What happened to that book on Russian history?
没人会对该死的俄罗斯历史感兴趣
No one is interested in Russian bloody history
菲洛梅娜
翻译/时间轴 JokerChow
个人制作 请勿商用
以前没见过你
Haven't seen you any place.
你从哪里来
Where're you from?
从利默里克来吗
Are you from Limerick?
你好 菲洛梅娜
Hello, Philomena.
神父
Father.
近来可好
How are you been?
你新换的髋关节怎么样
How's your new hip?
很好 是钛合金的
Oh, it's very good,it's titanium.
有段日子没见你了
Haven't seen you for a while.
我来点根蜡烛
I just came into and light a candle.
为某个特殊的人
Someone special?
是的
Yes.
我喜欢你的裙子
I like your dress.
你自己做的吗
Did you make it yourself?
不 我从店里买的
No I bought it in a shop.
我姑妈不让我跟你这样的陌生人说话
Anyway, me auntie told me I'm not to talk to strange men like you
你让他碰你了吗
Did you let him put his hands on you?
你很享受你的罪孽吗
Did you enjoy your sin
你把短裤脱下了吗
Did you take your knickers down?
回答希尔德嘉德修女 脱了吗
Answer Sister Hildegarde,did you take them down?
是的
Yes.
院长修女
Reverend Mother,
学校从没告诉过我们怀孩子是怎么回事
the school never told us anything about babies.
你母亲没跟你说过吗
Did your mother not tell you?
她母亲十年前去世了
Her mother died ten years ago.
上帝保佑她
God rest her soul.
别怪修女们无情
But don't dare to blame the sisters!
耻辱是你自己造成的
You are the cause of this shame.
伤风败俗
You and your indecency!
我不知道怎么办
I don't know what to do!
必须找个医生
We must to get a doctor.
婴儿的方向不对 这是臀位
The child is the wrong way round. it's breech!
一切都在上帝的掌握中
It's in God's hands now.
痛苦是她的赎罪
The pain is her penance.
天主圣母,仁慈之母
Hail, Holy Queen, Mother of Mercy,
别让他们把我的孩子丢在外面
Don't let them put my babay in the ground.
外面太冷太黑
It's cold there,it's dark there.
半小时之内帮他们关上灯
Just go up and turn their lights out in half an hour.
她难道不知道你有正经的工作
Doesn't she know you've got a proper job?
她缺人手 我只是代个班
She's short staffed,just fill in.
我午夜之前回来
I'll be home before midnight.
妈 怎么了
What is it mum?
你还好吗
Are you alright?
他是谁
Who's he?
今天是他生日 他50岁了
It's his birthday,he will be 50 today.
是个男孩
It's a boy.
马丁
Oh,Martin!
你好 大卫
Oh,hello David
凯斯你认识的
Keith you know.
莎莉·米契尔
Sally Mitchell
这是马丁·西克史密斯 曾经是BBC驻莫斯科记者
this is Martin Sixsmith, used to be the BBC's man in Moscow.
还有华盛顿
And Washington.
还当过政府的高级顾问
And then became a spin doctor for the government,
直到后来出了点岔子
until it all went a bit tits up.
这样总结恰当吗 马丁
Is that a fair summation Martin?
很恰当
That's fair enough.
我常说 常在河边走
I always say if you shovel shit for long enough,
哪能不湿鞋
eventually you'll get some on your shoes.
可你连头都湿了 怎么弄的
Yes,you got it on your head,how did you manage that?
你目前在做什么
What are you up to at the moment?
我正考虑写一本俄罗斯历史的书
I'm thinking of writing a book. On Russian history
或者别的 也许重回新闻界
Or something else. Maybe get back to journalism
我记得你
I remember you!
就是你写了那封糟糕的电子邮件
You're the one who sent that terrible e-mail saying
说911是个掩埋坏消息的好日子
it was a good day to bury bad news on 911
不是 是别人写的
No,I don't.That was someone else.
我还以为是你
I thought it was you.
这是个普遍的误解
That's a common mistake.
那是一年之后 玛格丽特公主葬礼那天
a year later, on the day of Princess Margaret's funeral
我发了封电邮说
I send an e-mail saying
让我们确定一下
let's make sure
今天唯一"埋葬"的
the only thing we "bury" inverted commas today
是玛格丽特公主
is Princess Margaret.
略有区别
It's slightly different.
区别大了
It's very different.
你如果想重回新闻界
Well if you want to get back into journalism,
就和莎莉谈谈
you should talk to Sally.
噢 我只是做
Oh I just do, you know,
伤感故事 情感类的
sob stories, human interest stuff
不见得合你口味
not really your cup of tea is it.
但是我倒很愿意看一看
But I'll be happy to have a look
如果你有什么好的想法
if you want to push any ideas my way?
谢谢
Yes please
请给我一杯灰皮诺
Excuse me, a glass of Pinot Grigio?
只有红葡萄酒和白葡萄酒
It's just red or white.
白葡萄酒
Oh White please.
我不小心听到你是位记者
I couldn't help over hearing you were a journalist.
我认识一个女人
I know a woman,
她未成年时生下一个孩子
and she had a baby when she was a teenager
这个秘密她守了五十年
she kept it a secret for fifty years
我想查清楚
I need found out today.
那些修女把孩子从她身边带走
Sorry,the baby was taken from her by these nuns
强行送去收养
then they made her have it adopted.
她一直守着这个秘密
And she kept it a secret all this time
我目前正在写一本书
I'm working on a book at the moment
关于俄罗斯历史
about Russian history
我正忙于这个
That's my thing.
你讲的这件事
what you're talking about would be
是情感类题材
a human interest story,
我不做这个
I don't do this.
为什么不
Why not?
因为情感故事是一种委婉的说法
Because human interest story is euphemism for
写的都是那些脆弱 胆怯 无知的人
stories about vulnerable, weak-minded, ignorant, people
用来填补报纸版面
to fill up the pages of newspapers
受众是那些脆弱 胆怯 无知的人
read by vulnerable, weak-minded, ignorant people
不是说你
Not that you are
总之 祝愿你能找到他
and,anyway,I hope you find him
我要是写个情感故事怎样
Do you think if I do a human interest story?
你好 你一定是菲洛梅娜了 我是马丁
Hello I'm Martin, you must be Philomena.
你好 马丁
Hello Martin.
你好
Hello again.
我们的位子在那边
we got a table through here...
左边
just the left
我要为那晚道歉
I must apologize the other night,
我当时状态很糟
caught me at a bad moment...
没关系 很高兴你设法找到我了
That'alright,I'm just glad you managed to track me down.
希望你别介意来这里
Hope you don't mind coming here
这是我妈最喜欢的餐厅
it's mum's favourite.
不 这地方很好
Oh no it's very nice.
菲洛梅娜 你好吗
So Philomena how are you?
我很好
I'm all right.
我去年做了髋关节置换手术
I had a hip replacement last year Martin,
比之前好多了
it's much better than the bone one I had before
是钛合金的 不会腐蚀
and it's ti-tanium so it wouldn't rust.
不错 你应该像铁皮人那样给它上油
It's good job you'd ought to have it oiled like the Tin Man
是吗
Oh is that right?
不 我是说 像绿野仙踪里那样
No no,I mean, like the Wizard of Oz.
他只是开玩笑 妈
He's just joking mum.
我开玩笑的
It was just a joke.
我母亲双腿膝盖都患了晚期关节炎
My mother has advanced osteoarthritis in both her knees.
要来点沙拉吗
Shall we get some salad?
好的
Salad,yes
简是我们家最聪明的
Jane's the clever one in our family.
她作为一个成人学生进了大学
She went to university as a mature student
比应届生年龄大
you know, when you're quite old.
你上的什么大学 马丁
Where did you go Martin
我猜是牛桥
Oxbridge I'll bet.
你调侃我吗 是牛津
You've ramble me.Oxford yes.
我就知道你不是笨蛋
I knew you weren't a duffer.
我以前去过Harvester餐厅
I've been a while in a Harvester before.
在伦敦也有店吗
Do they not have them in London?
有 我喜欢在我住处附近用餐
No I tend to go to a little local place, near where I live.
在哪里
And where's that?
骑士桥
Knightsbridge.
那一定很贵
Oh well that must be expensive.
我喜欢在上面加一些吐司丁
I love these pieces of toast on mine
你结婚了吗 马丁
And are you married Martin?
是的 和凯特结婚二十年了
Yes. I am, to Kate.20years
很好 很好
that's good. That's grand...
你要知道 我很爱他
I did love him, you know
我把这些事在心里埋藏了五十年
I've kept what happened to me buried away for 50 years.
我父亲把我交给修女
My father just left me with the nums.
他觉得很丢脸 告诉别人我死了
He was so shamed,he told everyone I was dead.
我家人从没去看过我
My family never visit me.
生下孩子之后
After you'd had your baby
就要在修道院待四年
you had to stay in the Abbey for four years,
为了偿还收留你的修女们
In order to repay the sisters for taking you in,
你必须干活
you had to work.
最差的是洗衣房的工作
The worst jobs were in the laundry,
我就被送到那里
and that's where they put me.
一周干活七天
I worked there seven days a week,
四年我一直在那
the whole time I was there.
我和最要好的朋友凯瑟琳一起干活
I worked there with my best friend,Kathleen.
每天允许我们见孩子一个钟头
We were allowed to see our children for an hour a day,
仅此而已
that was all.
慢慢走 不许跑
Walk don't run!
妈咪
Mummy!
安东尼和凯瑟琳的女儿玛丽是最好的朋友
Anthony was best friends with Kathleen's daughter Mary
他俩形影不离
The two of them were inseparable.
看啊 他一步都不肯离开她
Look at that, he won't let her out of his sight.
怎么了
What's the matter?
厨房的女孩告诉我
Phil the girl in the kitchen said
芭芭拉修女今天把玛丽带到那个房间
Mother Barbara had Mary up at the house today
你觉得她想对她做什么
what do you think she wanted with her?
一定不会有事的
I'm sure it's nothing to worry about
等我一下
It won't be a minute.
菲儿 我现在有空
Phil,I got some free
凯瑟琳担心死了
Kathleen's worried sick.
她觉得 他们要把玛丽带走
She thinks they're going to take Mary away from her.
我告诉她如果他们要那么做的话
I told her if they were going to do that
肯定会事先告诉她
they'd tell her first for sure
别告诉任何人
you can't tell anyone about it.
爸爸一定很英俊
I'll bet his father was handsome.
是的
He was.
你怎么办到的
How did you get this
我借了一架布朗尼相机
I borrowed a Box Brownie and
趁院长不注意时拍的
took it when Reverend Mother wasn't looking.
谢谢你
Thank you
每当我看着安东尼的照片时
Whenever I look at that Anthony,
我都为安娜希尔塔默默祈祷
I say a little prayer for Anunciata,
她帮我接生 救了孩子一命
who saved his life when I gave birth to him.
她很久前就去世了
She died a long time ago,
要不是她拍照 我什么也没有
If she hadn't taken that, I'd have nothing.
所以你一直被困在那里
So you were just trapped there the whole time?
付他们一百英镑才能离开
If you leave, you should pay them a hundred pounds.
我上哪弄这笔钱
But where would I get that kind of money?
我又去哪儿
And where would I go?
那天的情景我记得很清楚
I remember that day so clearly.
我们都明白那辆大轿车一到 意味着什么
We all knew what it meant when a big car arrived.
凯瑟琳伤心欲绝
Kathleen was inconsolable.
她知道这次轮到玛丽了
She knew this time they'd come for Mary.
离开那里
Come away from there!
你在这干什么
What are you doing out here?
我肚子疼 希尔德嘉德修女
I had a stomach ache, Sister Hidegarde.
我来例假了
It's my time of the month.
又不是只有你一人这样
Well,you're not unique in that regard.
把心思放工作上就过去了
Put your mind to your work and it'll pass.
菲儿 唱诗班练习开始了
Phil, it's choir practice.
再不去你就有麻烦了
You'll be in trouble if you don't go
我通常喜欢唱歌
Normally, I loved to sing
在那里 为数不多能让我感到开心的事之一
it was one of the only things I enjoyed at that place.
可是我脑子里全是可怜的凯瑟琳
But all I could think about was poor Kathleen.
菲洛梅娜 他们把安东尼带走了
Philomena,they take Anthony,they take him away!
他在哪
Where's he?
安东尼
Anthony!
他们原本只想接走玛丽
They only come for Mary,
但是安东尼一步都不愿离开她
but Anthony wouldn't let her out of his sight.
他们不可分离
They were inseparable
他们对你做的一切太罪恶了
I think what they did to you was evil.
不不不 我不喜欢这个词
No I don't like that word.
不 罪恶很好
No,evil's good.
就故事而言
Story wise.
有些修女 人很好
Some of them were nice.
当时是臀位分娩
It was a breech birth
她们连止痛药都不给她
and they wouldn't even give her painkillers.
非常好
Excellence.
还是就故事而言
Again,story wise.
我们能找那些修女谈谈吗
So can we go and talk to these nuns?
可以试试
We could try,
也许你比我妈运气好点
maybe you'll have more luck than mum's had.
这些年我几次向他们打听他在哪里
I've been several times over the years to ask where he was.
他们很热心
They were very helpful
跟过去不一样
it's not like it used to be.
他们说 会试着帮我追寻他的下落
They said they'd try and trace him for me.
但他们没有
But they haven't?
没有
No.
你能帮我找到他吗 马丁
Can you help me find him Martin?
嗯 这是个很有趣的故事
Well, it's an very interesting story.
下周我要带妈妈去爱尔兰几天
I'm taking mum to Ireland next week for a few days
你不如跟我们一起
why don't you come along with us
你可以和她一起去罗斯克里
and you can visit Roscrea with her?
我们的车很宽敞
Oh yes there's plenty of room
是沃克斯豪尔骑士
it's a Vauxhall Cavalier.
不用了 谢谢你
Oh no, I mean thank you,
我喜欢坐飞机
I like to fly.
你好 抱歉我迟到了
Hello, sorry I'm a little late.
你好 马丁
Hello Martin.
租的车出了点问题
Bit of trouble with the hire car.
真好 不是吗 简
Oh it's lovely, isn't it Jane.
我能明白你为何不愿意跟我们挤骑士车了
I can see why you wouldn't want to squash up with us in the Cavalier.
不 不是这样的
No.It wasn't that,
只是还有其他的事要办
it was just had a few things to do.
你确定不让我一起去 妈
Are you sure you don't want me to come with you mum?
你不一起
You're not coming?
不 我们俩去就行了
No,I told Jane we'll be fine on our own,
就我们俩 是吗 马丁
just the two of us, isn't that right Martin.
是的 很好
Yes. Fine.
我把零食放你包里了
I've put some things in your bag.
谢谢你 马丁
Thanks Martin.
这是什么车
What kind of car is this?
宝马
It's a BMW.
德国车
That's German.
吃块Tune吗 马丁
Would you like a Tune Martin?
Tune 一种糖 有"曲子"之意
我哼歌 你伴奏吗
If I hum it, will you play it?
不 你想吃块Tune吗
No, would you like a Tune?
谢谢
Thanks.
能带来好运
For good luck.
我小时候一直以为
I always thought
圣克里斯多夫有点像米老鼠
Saint Christopher was a bit of Mickey Mouse Saint
我以前是辅祭儿童
I used to be an altar boy
马丁 你相信上帝吗
Do you believe in God Martin?
怎么说呢
Well, where do you start.
我一直认为很难
I always thought that's a very difficult question
给出一个简单的回答
to give a simple answer,
你信吗
do you?
我信
Yes.
罗斯克里修道院
你还好吧
You all right?
我很好
I'm fine.
我很幸运 马丁
I'm one of the lucky ones Martin.
有些母亲和孩子
Some of the mothers and babies
分娩时都没活下来
didn't even survive the childbirth.
需要什么帮助吗
Can I help you?
我是菲洛梅娜·李
I'm Philomena Lee.
之前预约过
I made an appointment.
请进 菲洛梅娜
Oh yes come in Philomena.
这位是我朋友马丁·西克史密斯 十点新闻的记者
And this is my friend Martin Sixsmith News At Ten.
是BBC 但我已经不在那了
BBC news actually, but not any more
噢 你好
Oh, hello
克莱尔修女马上就到
Sister Claire will be with you shortly.
谢谢
Thank you.
我能用下洗手间吗
May I use the bathroom?
在楼下的...
It's down stairs...
我知道在哪
I know where it is.
我给你们倒点茶好吗
Would I give you both some tea?
好的 谢谢
Yes,thank you.
希尔德嘉德修女肖像 1957年10月
芭芭拉院长和希尔德嘉德修女
在罗斯克里修道院外
我所有的爱 简
安东尼
Anthony!
你好
Hello!
噢 你好
Oh, hello.
我是克莱尔修女
I'm sister Claire.
我刚才在欣赏简·曼斯菲尔德的照片
I Just admiring your picture of Jayne Mansfield.
不 那是简·拉塞尔
No that's Jane Russell.
两人皆为好莱坞黄金时代女星
简·曼斯菲尔德是金发
Jayne Mansfield was the blonde one.
当然 她们名气都很大
Of yes of course, I mean they were both very big
她们两人 都有很辉煌的
I mean the two of them, they were huge.
演艺生涯
Their careers.
哪一个死于车祸来着
Which one died in the car crash?
简·曼斯菲尔德
Jayne Mansfield, yes.
为什么挂她的照片
Why is she on the wall?
不好意思 我没听清你的名字
Sorry, I didn't catch your name?
马丁 西克史密斯
Martin Sixsmith.
马丁·西克史密斯 十点新闻
He's Martin Sixsmith, News At Ten.
我以前在BBC工作 但现在不是了
I was in BBC. But I'm not any more.
你好 菲洛梅娜 非常高兴见到你
Hello Philomena, very nice to meet you
我是克莱尔修女
I'm sister Claire
菲洛梅娜 你上次来这里是什么时候
What was the last time you came to see us Philomena?
那是在你来之前 克莱尔修女
It was well before your time Sister Claire.
我跟希尔德嘉德修女通了电话
I spoke to Sister Hildegarde on the telephone,
当我到这里
and when I came here
她身体不好 不能和我见面
she wasn't well enough to see me.
她还在这里
She's still with us,
但非常虚弱
but she's very frail now.
马丁 吃点黄油果子面包
Oh Martin, Have some buttered brack.
很美味 有点像潘多尔切
Very nice, like a sort of a Pandolce
这是水果面包 马丁
It's fruit bread Martin.
是的 我知道 非常好
Yes, I know it's lovely.
我不知道上次他们有没有告诉你 菲洛梅娜
Well now I don't know if they told you last time Philomena,
但我们绝大多数的档案
but most of our records
都毁于一场火灾
were destroyed in the big fire-
火灾
Fire?
那是我来之前
It was before my time.
所以 恐怕我无法提供任何信息
So I'm afraid I have no news.
我一直去做弥撒
I still go to mass
我不想造成什么麻烦
I don't want to cause any fuss
或是指责谁
or point the finger at anybody,
或以任何方式怪罪教会
or blame the church in any way.
我只想知道他是否还安好
I just want to know that he's all right
甚至都不用见他
I don't even need to see him.
我能想象出
I have visions of him
他无家可归的样子 没人疼爱他
and he's homeless and nobody loves him.
菲洛梅娜
Philomena
我们无法抚平你的创伤
we can't take away your pain,
但我们能和你携手度过难关
but we can walk through it with you, hand in hand.
那些老修女
these older nuns
抱歉打断一下
Sorry interrupt
她们也许能回忆起一些细节
Perhaps they might remember a few details?
大多数都已经过世了
Most of them have passed away.
那些在世的呢
What about the ones that haven't?
我觉得不大可能和她们沟通
I don't think you'll get much sense out of them.
能试一试吗
Can We try?
我认为这不可能
I don't think that's going to be possible.
为什么不
Why not?
我很乐意回答菲洛梅娜提出的任何问题
I'm happy to answer any questions that Philomena has.
我是在问问题
I'm asking a question.
可你是记者
You're a journalist.
曾经是
I used to be.
马丁是天主教徒
Martin's a Roman Catholic.
是的 嗯 曾经是
Yes,well, I used to be.
如果能和菲洛梅娜单独谈 我会觉得更自在点
I'd feel more comfortable if I could speak to Philomena in private.
你好 有什么能帮你的
Hello,can I help you?
抱歉 我只是在
Sorry, I was just erm...
你在找什么东西吗
Are you looking for something?
那边是什么
What's down here?
那是私人住所
Those are private quarters.
我在外面等
I'll wait outside
分娩时死亡的母亲和孩子
艾丝琳·德夫林 14岁 安息
对不起 我刚在周围转转
Sorry I was just having a look around
她跟你说了什么
What did she say to you?
她说你是个记者
She said you were a journalist
你想利用我
and you were trying to manipulate me
对你说话要小心
I should be careful what I say to you.
她还给了我这个
She also gave me this.
你不想亲自打开吗
Don't you want to open it?
这是一份你签字的协议 1955年
It's a contract signed by you,in 1955.
"我在此永久放弃对我的孩子安东尼·李的全部权利
I hereby relinquish full claim forever to my said child Anthony Lee
我保证绝不企图去
and I further undertake never to attempt to see,
看望 干涉 向这个孩子提出任何要求
interfere with or make any claim to the said child
在将来的任何时刻"
at any future time"
我再也找不到他了
I'll never find him.
如果他们强迫你签这份协议
If they coerced you in any way to sign that piece of paper
可以起诉他们
we can challenge them legally.
没人强迫我
No one coerced me Martin.
我自愿签的
I signed of my own free will.
很奇怪不是吗
It's funny isn't it,
所有那些能帮你找到他的文件全被毁了
all pieces of paper designed to help you find him has been destroyed.
谁能想到 唯一一份
But guess what? The one piece of paper
旨在阻止你找到他的文件
designed to stop you from finding him
却被完好地保留下来
has been lovingly preserved.
上帝用他无限的智慧
God in his infinite wisdom
使它免于火灾
decided to spare that from the flames
我签字是因为
I signed it because
我相信我犯了重罪 必须接受惩罚
I believed I'd committed a terrible sin I had to be punished
而且更糟糕的是
And what made it so much worse, was
我还很享受
that I enjoyed it.
做爱
The sex.
太美妙了 简直欲仙欲死
Oh, it was wonderful. I thought I was floating on air.
他很英俊
He was so handsome
他把我搂在怀里的样子
and the way he held me in his arms
我都不知道我有阴蒂
thing is I didn't even know I had a clitoris
做爱之后 我觉得
And after I had the sex, I thought
任何看起来美好的事情 一定有问题
anything that feels so lovely must be wrong.
去他妈的天主教徒
Fucking Catholics.
抱歉
Sorry.
我当了三十年护士
I spent thirty years as a nurse,
听过比这更难听的
I've heard worse than that.
这就是上帝赋予我们性欲的原因吗
It's why would God bestow on us a sexual desire
为了压制它
which he then wants us to resist?
这是他发明的古怪游戏吗
Is it some weird game that he's invented
为了排遣作为全能上帝的无聊感
to alleviate the boredom of being omnipotent?
难以琢磨
Baffles me,
我还以为我很聪明
and I think I'm pretty clever.
也许你没那么聪明
Well maybe you're not.
进展如何
How did it go?
什么 从那些不仁慈的修女那里?
What, from the Sisters of Little Mercy?
只是喝茶吃点心
Just tea and cake then.
就没别的了 妈
That's all they've ever given mum.
不是他们的错 简
It wasn't their fault Jane,
所有档案都在火灾中被烧了
they had a fire and all the records were lost.
不了 谢谢 该睡觉了
No thank you it's past your bedtime.
不 刚倒的 让我喝完
Well he's poured it now.
晚安 马丁
Night Martin.
晚安 简
Night Jane.
晚安 菲洛梅娜 好好睡吧
Good night Philomena.Sleep well.
干杯
Cheers.
去了修道院
Been up to the Abbey?
是的 显然那里变化很大
Yes. Yes, it's obviously very different now.
修女也换了
nuns are different,
不是抹大拉的马利亚姑娘们在时的那群修女了
not the same ones they had when the Magdalen girls were there.
抹大拉的马利亚 被耶稣拯救的妓女
她们都不在了
They're all gone now!
我们招待过几个人
We've had a few staying here,
来这里寻找他们孩子的下落
looking to find what happened to their sons or daughters.
没什么人得到满意的结果
There's not many of them gets any joy from there.
有场大火把一切都烧毁了
a big fire that destroyed everything
你知道是怎么回事吗
Do you know how did that started
我觉得是她们放的火
I should think they put a match to it.
谁
Who?
那些修女
The Sisters.
在田野后面放了一场大火
Sure they had a great fire out the back in the field.
修道院没失火
So the Abbey wasn't on fire?
他们烧了一个该死的大火堆
They had a bloody big bonfire,
烧掉了所有档案 成千上万的
burnt all the records. Thousands of "em.
为什么
Why?
多年前的事了
This was years ago.
我猜他们是为把孩子卖到美国的事感到不安
I suppose they were embarrassed about selling all them babies to America.
他们怕人告发
They don't want people telling tales.
说话的我妈
That's me mother.
你说他们把孩子卖给美国人
You say they were sold to Americans?
许多美国佬来爱尔兰找孩子
A lot of the Yanks came over to Ireland to look for babies.
只有他们买得起
They were the only ones who could afford them.
一千英镑
A thousand pounds.
简·拉塞尔从德里买了个孩子 1952年
Jane Russell bought a baby. From Derry, in 1952.
不敢相信 卖孩子
That's unbelievable,babies were sold?
她来我们这里要波旁威士忌
She came in here looked for Bourbon
我们只能用爱尔兰威士忌代替
but they had to give her a glass of Paddy instead.
如果你是天主教徒 并且有一千英镑
If you're a catholic with a thousand pounds,
你就能买个孩子
you can buy a baby.
简·拉塞尔买了一个带回家
Jane Russell bought one to take home with her.
但这事本不允许谈论
But I'm not allowed to discuss
我能理解
No I can see that
干杯
Cheers
莎莉你说过
Sally you told me
如果有什么好想法就给你打电话
to call you if I came up with something,
正好天上掉馅饼
it just sort of fell into my lap
接着说
Go on
相当有趣
It's quite interesting ,
关于人们寻找家人的故事
things about people search for their family trees
爱尔兰离散族裔
and the whole Irish Diaspora
别用离散族裔这个词 马丁
Don't use words like Diaspora Martin.
我都拼不好 别人更不知道什么意思
I can't spell it and people don't know what it means.
意思是
It just means
不不不 我感兴趣的不是这词的含义
No no.I'm genuinely not interested in what it means.
好人是谁 坏人是谁
Who are the goodies, who are the baddies?
是个爱尔兰小老太太
Well,it's about a little old Irish lady,
一名退休护士
a retired nurse,
寻找她失散已久的儿子
who is searching for her long lost son
孩子刚生下就被人夺走
who is taken snatch from her at birth,
被那些坏修女
by evil nuns.
结局如何
So how does it end?
要么是悲剧 要么皆大欢喜
and it's got to be really happy or really sad.
他是IBM董事长还是流浪汉 不重要
either he's the chairman of IBM, or a hobo,doesn't matter.
五十年的渺无音信
The years melted away as a fifty year silence
被两个简单的词打破
was broken with two simple words:
你好 妈妈
"Hello mum".
我现在就可以写出来
I could write it now.
我都不知道你这么会煽情
I didn't know you were so cynical.
我的猜测是安东尼被送往美国收养
My guess is Anthony adopted and sent to America
修道院专门与美国人做交易
The Abbey dealt exclusively with American customers.
他们卖孩子
They sold babies.
他们只是为了给孩子更好的生活
They only try to give them a better life.
为了赚钱
Try to make money out of him.
这就是问题
That's the problem
我今早给科克的圣心收养院打了电话
I got through to the Sacred Heart Adoption Society in Cork this morning
他们给我转到爱尔兰收养局
they just referred me to the Irish Adoption Board,
对方又把我转给圣心收养院
who referred me back to the Sacred Heart Adoption Society.
跟你兜圈子
Sending you round in circles
毫无帮助
Then it got helpless
但昨晚我和华盛顿的联系人谈了
but I spoke to some contacts from my Washington days last night,
在美国可以有途径追踪
avenues that can be pursued in America
障碍是
The stumbling block, of course, is
我只能替你走到这一步 菲洛梅娜
that I can only get so far speaking on your behalf Philomena.
你作为他的母亲
But as you're his mother,
他们有义务向你提供所有信息
they are duty bound to provide you with the information.
你的意思是让我母亲和你一起去美国
Are you suggesting my mother goes to America with you?
如果你愿意的话
If you wanted to.
我的编辑同意报销费用
My editor has agreed for the bill
你觉得如何 和马丁去美国一趟
How would you feel about that, going to America?
我不知道
I don't know.
你愿意的话我可以随你一起
I could come with you if you like?
不不不 你还要工作
No no no.you've got your work.
我更担心的是
I'm more worried about
马丁一路上和我这个愚蠢的老太太
Martin going all that way with a daft old woman like me.
我不认为你愚蠢
I don't think you're daft
去你的
Oh go away with you.
或老
or old
我愿意去
I think I'd like to go.
我想知道安东尼有没有想过我
I want to know if Anthony ever thought about me,
因为我每天都在思念他
cos I've thought about him every day.
华盛顿 很好
Oh,Washinton,lovely
你自己打的包吗
Did you pack your baggage yourself?
我女儿帮我的
My daughter helped me.
这待遇真高级 马丁
I'm getting royal treatment Martin.
感觉像教皇一样
I feel like the Pope
保护你的髋关节
well, save your hip
有什么好看的书吗
Have any interesting book?
我的刚读完
I've just finishing mine
有些枯燥
it's a bit dull ,
关于十月革命
about the October revolution
政治价码
it's all just political horse-trading
我的也是讲马的
Mine was about horses too.
讲一个叫罗伯特的小伙子
It was about this fella Robert
他和一个贵妇订了婚
and he's engaged to this duchess
他是医生的儿子
and he's the son of a doctor
非常出色
so he's done very well for himself
但那个女人很差劲
but this woman oh she's terrible
她很虚荣
is vain as she like
总爱照镜子
and always looking herself in the mirror
之类的
that's sort of thing
她觉得他像一潭死水一样乏味
And she thinks he's dull as ditch-water
所以他开始对马感兴趣
so he takes up an interest in the horses
这样才能融入上层社会
because that way he's getting upper classes
后来他在马厩遇见了一个姑娘
and of course he meets the girl down the stables
她出身卑微
and she's not even a doctor's daughter
她父亲是农场工人
her father's just a farmhand and
他只有一只脚
he only has one foot
但不管怎样他俩相爱了
but anyway of course they fall in love,
他现在左右为难
and he's now torn between
娶了贵妇 他就能当公爵
becoming a duke because when he marries her
成为领主之类的
he'll become lord of the manor and all that sort of thing,
而他爱的那个马厩姑娘
and the stable girl who he loves
名下一个子儿也没有
but hasn't a penny to her name
到了婚礼那天
so the big day's coming the wedding
那姑娘 啊 她太可爱了
and this girl, oh she is lovely,
她说罗伯特必须尽他的义务
she says Robert has to do his duty
都已经定好了
and he's already spoken for
他试着礼服
and he's being measured up for his suit
但是心不在焉
but you can tell his heart's not in it
因为他一直想着马和马厩姑娘
cos all the while he's thinking about the horses and the stable girl.
所有人都在教堂等他
So they're all there waiting for him in the church,
达官贵人们
the hoi polloi,
但事情是这样的 马丁
but the thing is Martin
那个贵妇
this duchess
只想刁难罗伯特
she just wants Robert to spite the fella
这是她的真正意图
she's really after
到最后贵妇发现
then towards the end the duchess finds out that
马厩姑娘想打罗伯特的主意
the stable girl has designs on Robert
在那之前 姑娘的瘸腿老爹死了
but before that the father without the foot dies
她爹临死前对罗伯特说
but before he does he says to Robert
追随你的内心
"follow your heart"
然后贵妇对马厩姑娘下了驱逐令
and then the duchess gives the stable girl her marching orders
她开始收拾行囊
and she packs her things
外面有辆小马车等着她
there's a pony and trap waiting for her outside and
她上了马车
when she climbs into it
问你知道去哪儿吗
she asks do you know where we're going?
车夫转过身来
And the driver turns round
这不就是心上人罗伯特吗
and if it isn't yer man Robert.
他说道
And he says
我要带你去一个再也不受伤害的地方
I'm taking you to a place where no one can hurt you anymore
我根本没想到这个结局 马丁
Well, I didn't see that coming Martin,
一百万年也想不到
not in a million years.
真是个不错的惊喜
It's nice to have a surprise.
听起来很引人入胜
Sounds like a real page turner.
我可以借你看
You can borrow it.
算了
That'ok
不 我已经看完了
No no.I've just finished it now.
我感觉像是已经看了一遍了
I almost feel like I've read it
《拖鞋和马蹄铁》
The Slipper And The Horseshoe
噢 还是一个系列的
Oh,this is the series of them
香槟还是鸡尾酒
Champagne or Buck's Fizz?
不用了 谢谢
No,thank you.
免费的
Free
哎呦 给我来杯鸡尾酒
I say! I'll have a Buck's Fizz!
谢谢
Thank you.
真好 马丁
Well, that's lovely.Martin
我坐过瑞安航空 什么都要花钱
You have to pay for everything on Ryan Air.
他们不算高级
Well,they don't have top class
阿莱克斯 你好吗
Alex, how are you?
自从你离开单位 就没见过你
Not seen you since you left the department.
我还打算给你打电话
I was gonna call you actually
我们还是朋友吗
Still friends?
当然
Yes of course.
我希望你别以为是我告的密
Listen, I hope you didn't think I dropped you in it?
说实话 不用担心 这是战争迷雾
Don't worry about it honestly, fog of war.
是啊 连带伤害
Yeh, collateral damage.
你去美国干什么 采访选举
So what are you up to? Off to the primaries?
是的 - 不 他帮我找...
Yes,yes. - No.He's helping me look...
采访一个情感类的故事
It's a human interest story.
祝好运 我得赶快回去了
Well good luck with it.I'd better scoot back.
好的
Ok
不好意思 马丁 我们是不是该装作不认识
I'm sorry Martin should we pretend we don't know each other?
不 他只是我以前的同事
No,he is just someone I used to work,
政治顾问 我只是想回避他
a spin doctor,I just try to avoid him
那边是头等舱吗
Is that First Class in there?
工作补贴
It's a perk of the job.
坐头等舱
Just because you're in first class
又不代表他是头等人
it doesn't make you a first class
他还好了
He's all right.
让他去屎吧
I think he needs a good swipe of shite.
你说的没错
Yes.you're probably right.
马丁 你枕头上也有巧克力吗
Martin, did you have a chocolate on your pillow?
是的
Yes.I did.
地球另一边的生活
How the other half lives,see?
瞧这景色
look at that view.
我那边只能看到空调管道
Mine is of the air condition ducts.
档案室的卡罗琳打来的
Caroline from the records office.
这是推测
Well,that's conjecture.guess work.
很好的推测 把名单发给我
Good guess work.Send over the long list,
好极了 明早再和你联系 好的再见
Great.Fablulous.I'll talk to you in the morning.Okay,bye-bye.
出去散步吗 倒一下时差
Shall we go for a walk, try and shake off our jet lag?
你说一直想看林肯纪念堂
You said you wanted to see the Lincoln Memorial?
林肯以后再看
Well, we can go to see Mr. Lincoln.
现在还是看电视吧
Or, we could watch on my television...
绝地奶霸
Big Momma's House
一个黑人打扮成胖女人
It's about a little black man who pretends to be a fat black lady.
我以前看过片段
They showed some of it on the tv
他被追着满大街跑
and they're all chasing after him
特别滑稽 马丁
it looked hilarious Martin.
真不可思议
Isn't he wonderful.
我一直想亲眼看看他坐在那把大椅子上
I've always wanted to see him in his big chair.
他的确是个大个子
Well he was big man.
6.4英尺 最高的美国总统
Literally.Six foot four. Tallest American president.
我能看得出 坐着还显得那么高
I can see that. He's tall even sitting down.
我有个朋友
I had a friend
她女儿花钱带她去佛罗里达
and her daughter paid for her to go to Florida
祝她七十大寿
for her seventieth birthday
她跟我说
and she said
菲儿 餐厅食物的分量
"Phil, the size of the portions
多的你都不敢相信
you wouldn't believe".
我来给你拍张快照
I'm going to take your quick picture.
文章上用的?
Is this for the article?
我有点担心
Only I'm a little bit worried you see,
如果找到他
because if I find him
他也许不赞成我把一切告诉记者
he might be very disapproving of talking to the papers.
家事应该很隐私的
Families are very private things.
好的 站在那里
Alright,go and stand by there.
说的没错 但追寻他是很大一笔开销
that's true, but tracking him down's a very expensive business
所以就算是等价交换了
so it's like a  quid pro quo.
什么意思
What does that mean?
就是一物换一物
It means this for that.
别担心
But don't worry
你不满意的话我不会发表
I won't write anything you're unhappy with.
只是讲述事实
Just the truth.
这就是我担心的
That's the thing I'm worried about.
我该面带微笑还是严肃点
Should I smile or should I be serious?
拍一张开心的 一张不开心的
Let's do one happy, one not so happy
我好害怕
I'm getting scared
越来越近了
now we're getting closer.
这么多年 不知道安东尼是否遭受不幸
All these years, wondering whether Anthony was in trouble,
或是进监狱
or in prison
天知道
or goodness knows what.
只要我一刻没了解真相
As long as I didn't know,
我就能一直安慰自己
I could always tell myself that
他正在某个角落过得很幸福 一切安好
he was happy somewhere, and he was doing all right.
可要是他死在越战怎么办
But what if he died in Vietnam?
或失去双腿
Or came back with no legs,
或是流落街头
or lived on the street.
别自寻烦恼
Don't upset yourself.
不知道的事就是不知道
We don't know what we don't know.
面对事实的时候应对好就行了
We'll just have to deal with that when we get there.
他要是个瘾君子怎么办 马丁
What if he was a drug addict Martin,
要有肥胖症怎么办
what if he was obese?
肥胖症
Obese?
我看过一个纪录片说
I watched this documentary that said
许多美国人都是大胖子
a lot of Americans are huge
万一他也是怎么办
what if that's happened to him?
怎么会想到他有肥胖症
But what on earth makes you think he'd be obese?
因为食物分量很大
Because of the size of the portions.
你好
Hello?
不 我这有浴衣 菲洛梅娜
No,I've got a both robe,Philomena.
对 每个房间都有两件
Yes,there're two in every room
还有两双拖鞋
And slippers.
你只是有点时差反应
Ok.You just a little bit jetlag,
躺下休息吧
just try to get lie down.
好的 晚安
Alright,good night.
大家都好吗
how's everyone?
都很好
We're all good,
丹尼赢了橄榄球比赛 还触地得分了
Danny won his rugby match today and he scored a try.
真棒
That's fantastic
菲洛梅娜怎么样
How's Philomena?
我终于明白了
Well, I finally seen, first hand,
读者文摘 每日邮报 和浪漫小说给人影响有多深
what a lifetime's diet of Reader's Digest, the Daily Mail and romantic fiction can do to a person's brain.
她一直对宾馆员工念叨他们多友好
She keeps telling all the hotel staff how kind they are.
她肯定以为他们是志愿者
she must think they're volunteers.
她今天和四个人说 他们每个都是"万里挑一"
She tell four people today who were all, "one in a million".
这是怎样的概率啊
What are the chances of that?
别贫了 她只是个爱尔兰小老太太
Oh come on she's just a little old Irish lady.
怎么了
Is something alright?
马丁 之前想跟你说 可是忘了
Martin I wanted to tell you something earlier but it slipped my mind,
本想打电话的 我又不记得号码
and I was going to tell you on the phone but I forgot the number,
马丁 我想说的是
What I want to say Martin is that
谢谢你帮我找儿子
Thank you for helping me to look for my son.
我知道你丢了工作
I know you got the sack from your job
不是十点新闻 是其他的
not News At Ten,the other one.
但他们的损失就是我的收获
But that their loss is my gain.
谢谢你
Thank you.
晚安 马丁
Good night Martin.
晚安 菲洛梅娜
Good night.Philomena.
你好 卡罗琳 我是马丁·西克史密斯
Hi Caroline it's Martin Sixsmith.
我想核对一下
I just wanted to check
移民资料
the file with the immigration cuttings
我知道你核对过了
I know you've checked,
给我发个链接好吗
but could you send me a link anyway
我们英国没有墨西哥人
we don't really have Mexicans in England,
但是有印度人
we have the Indians instead,
人人都爱咖喱
and everybody loves curry.
马丁 那边有蛋卷
Martin they've got omelettes over there,
薄饼
pancakes
还有华夫饼
and waffles and
什么馅的都有
any filling
还有麦片粥 培根 香肠
and cereals and bacon and sausage
要什么有什么 -- 我看见了
and anything you want
早餐都包括在房钱里面吗
The breakfast is included isn't it?
是的 我不饿
It is.I'm just too early
太早了还没什么胃口
My stomach hasn't woken up yet.
我也是
Mine wakes up before I do.
我要吃火腿 瑞士奶酪 和麦片粥
I'm having a ham and Swiss cheese omelette
给你也带点
shall I get you one?
不用了 我还不饿
No.I'm just not hungry.
要不来点蓝莓
Why don't you have some blueberries?
要咖啡吗
Coffee?
不了 谢谢
No thanks.
如果你想自取早餐
Okay if you want to help yourself to breakfast over there
冷热餐都有
we have a hot and cold buffet,
新鲜水果 麦片粥 -- 她刚告诉我
fresh fruit and cereal.-- She just told me.
松饼 各种口味的蛋卷
muffins, omelettes with a choice of filling.
早餐有什么我全知道
I know exactly what is available for breakfast.
还有现烤的薄饼
We also have fresh pancakes?
谢谢你
Thank you.
我们正在私人谈话
I'm trying to have a private conversation here.
抱歉 先生
My apologies sir.
别那么没礼貌
There's no need to be rude.
她人很好
She's a very nice person.
是的 她一定是万里挑一
Yes, I'm sure she's one in a million
或千里挑一
or one in a hundred thousand.
什么意思
What do you mean?
你至少跟十个人这么说了
You've said that to at least ten people.
我就计算一下
so that's just maths.
你高高在上时 应该对下面的人都好些
You should be nice to people on the way up
等你掉下来时 说不定还会遇到他们
because you might meet them again on the way down.
你们这些人应该认识到这点
You of all people would understand that.
我宁愿你对我更没礼貌
I'd rather you were rude to me
都别那样对他们
than the nice people who work here.
对不起
I'm sorry.
我只是在帮你找儿子
I'm trying to help you find your son,
这就是我们来的原因
that's why we're here.
安静一下
So have some quiet time?
你出生在墨西哥
Were you born in Mexico?
我来自奇瓦瓦
I'm from Chihuahua
你一定喜欢墨西哥玉米脆片
You must like nachos?
我外孙女娜塔莉让我喜欢上它了
My grand daughter Natalie got me into them.
我没去过墨西哥
I've never been to Mexico
但我相信一定是个好地方
I believe it's lovely
除了拐卖儿童
apart from the kidnappings
安东尼·李 移民资料
赫斯博士和太太 与两名家庭新成员玛丽和迈克尔
到达米德韦机场 两个孩子是从爱尔兰领养
迈克尔·赫斯 出生日期 1952年7月5日
迈克尔·赫斯 1952年生于爱尔兰
1955年随养父母到美国
老布什总统的首席法律顾问
里根执政时期共和党重要顾问
死于1995年8月15日
没有蓝莓了 我给你拿了些木莓
They've run out of blueberries so I got you raspberries instead.
对不起 我忘了要安静
I'm sorry. Quiet time.
这是我的安东尼
That's my Anthony.
他已经死了 是不是
He's dead... isn't he.
是的 对不起
Yes,I'm sorry.
真的对不起
I'm sorry.I'm so sorry.
他死了
He's dead.
谁死了
Who's dead?
那个儿子 8年前就死了
The son,he died 8 years ago.
天哪
Oh,dear.
死因是什么
What did he die of?
我不知道 没去查
I don't know, I didn't find out.
我人在机场
I'm at the airport
机场
The airport?
她想回家 和女儿在一起
she wants to get back, be with her daughter.
故事怎么办
What about the story?
他已经死了
Well,he's dead.
死或生 悲剧或喜剧
Dead or alive, happy or sad
都很好
they're both good.
想办法把这个故事写下去
Spin it, find a story.
听着 我要是留下 而她回去了
Look,if I stay here and she goes,
我找谁去问
no-one's going to answer my questions.
那就别让她走
Then keep her there.
什么 她现在很痛苦
What? Come on,she's in bits.
就好像再一次失去了他
It's like she's lost him all over again.
这句台词很不错 记下来
That's great write that line down.
你可是有合约在身
you signed a contract.
你是认真的
Are you serious?
是的 有新消息再打给我
Yes.Call me when you've got something.
抱歉 是我的编辑
Sorry,my editer.
看来要用那张不开心的照片了
It is suppose to use the not happy photo now.
是的
Yes,I suppose so.
我想起在游乐场那天
I remember that day at the fair,
他父亲装成老头逗我开心
his father made me laugh by pretending to be an old man.
我也装成老太太逗他开心
And then I made him laugh by pretending to be an old woman.
现在我成老太太了
And now I am one.
我永远都无法知道安东尼是否想起过我
I'll never know if Anthony ever thought about me.
我永远都没机会说对不起
I'll never be able to say sorry.
还有一小时就登机了
Start boarding for about one hour.
马丁 机票还可以改签吗
Tell me Martin.Do we have flexible tickets
是的 可以
Yes,I think so.
如果计划有变 就能改航班
You can change another flight if change your plans?
是的
Yes.
我们也许不该今天走
Suppose we didn't get on the airplane tonight.
我一直在这等一个征兆
Because I've sitting here waiting for sign.
但什么都没有
But haven't had one.
于是我决定在这里多待一段时间
So I made a decision myself I'd like to stay here longer
如果你打算这么做的话
Well,if that's what you want to do
是的
It is.
我想和认识他的人谈谈
I'd like to talk to someone who actually met him.
那我们留下
Then we'll stay
我收到了一张安东尼的照片
I've been sent a picture of Anthony
要看看吗
Do you want to see it?
噢
Oh?
好的
Yes please.
里根总统
President Reagan
是明天要和我们见面的女士发来的
It's from a woman we could meet tomorrow
她叫玛茜娅·韦勒
called Marcia Weller,
她曾经是安东尼的同事
she was a colleague of Anthony's
他看上去很聪明
He looks very smart.
喝一杯吗 白兰地
Now shall we have a drink? Brandy
啊 都没了
Oh they're all gone.
马丁 这个人好像你
Martin.This man looks just like you.
是我
It is me.
迈克尔·赫斯
Michael Hess.
我见过他 -- 在哪
I met him. Where?
在白宫
At the White House.
天哪
Oh dear God.
大概十年前 我还在BBC工作
It was 10years ago when I was with the BBC.
他什么样
What was he like?
我记不起了
I can't remember it.
共和党的事情
It was a Republican thing.
你好好想一想
You must remember something.
我们进去时他就在门口
He was by the door as we entered.
我还和他握了手
I shook hands with him.
怎么握的
What was the handshake did he have?
坚定有力
It was firm
如果他握手软弱无力 我一定记得很清楚
If I'd have remembered if a weak handshake.
可没人会在那个位置上软弱无力地握手
No-one would get to that position with a weak handshake
他握手有力  还有呢
So he had a firm handshake?What else?
他很聪明
He was smart.
我一直希望他聪明
Oh I always dressed him smart.
你能想起他说了什么吗
Did you remember anything he said?
"你好" 也许可能是"嗨"
Hello,or might be hi
他很彬彬有礼
He was polite.
他很聪明 握手很有力
He was smart, and he had a firm handshake.
他还说了"你好"
He said."Hello"
还说了"你好""你好"
He said."Hello"Hello
还很彬彬有礼  -- 太好了 马丁!
He was polite. -- Oh Martin!
我认识您儿子有十年了
I knew your son for about ten years.
他是里根和布什政府的高级法律顾问
He was senior legal counsel to both the Reagan and Bush administrations.
干得不错嘛
Didn't do too badly, did he?
他要是在我身边 永远也干不了这工作
He'd never have got a job like that if he'd stayed with me.
我想他会在麦克埃弗利斯上班
I think he would have worked at McEverleys.
是卡斯尔巴的一间律师事务所
They're a firm of solicitors in Castlebar.
他提起过爱尔兰吗 玛茜娅
Did he ever mention Ireland to you Marcia?
没有
I don't think so
但是我有他妹妹玛丽的电话
But I have a number for his sister, Mary,
和他一起从爱尔兰来的妹妹
who came from Ireland with him
我可以帮你联系她
I can put you in touch with her?
很好 非常好
Oh,great.That's excellent.
他看起来很开心
He looks very happy here,
这个小伙子是谁
who's this fella?
这是他的朋友 皮特
That's his, er, friend Pete.
你是他女朋友吧 玛茜娅
Were you his girlfriend Marcia?
不是
No.
我不知道你是否了解 他是同性恋
I don't know if you knew, but he was gay.
参加正式场合时我经常陪他
I used accompany him when he went to official functions
因为共和党排斥同性恋
because being gay was frowned upon in the Republican party.
但是他非常有魅力
But he was very charming and very charismatic.
跟我说说他有小孩吗
Tell me did he father any children
菲洛梅娜 玛茜娅刚才说了 他是同性恋
Philomena,Marcia just told us that Anthony was gay.
我一直都知道
Oh, I always knew that.
我想他也许是双性恋
I just thought he might have been bicurious.
我以前共事过的很多护士都是同性恋
A lot of the nurses I worked with were gay
其中有一个叫布兰登 他是双性恋
but one of them, called Brendan, told me he was bi-curious.
我觉得他不会那么坚决
I don't think he could make up his mind Marcia.
他没有孩子 抱歉
He didn't have any children. I'm sorry.
皮特爱他吗
Did Pete love him?
是的 爱他
Yes he did.
你怎么知道他是同性恋
How did you know he was gay?
他是个非常敏感的小男孩
Well, he was a very sensitive little boy.
这么些年我一直在想他也许是
And as the years rolled on I always wondered if he might be.
当我第一眼看见他穿粗布工作服的照片时
Then, when I saw that photograph of him in the dungarees,
我就认定了
well there was no doubt in my mind...
皮特 你觉得呢
Pete,what do you think?
我觉得它今天有点心情不好 有点暴躁
I think he is in a bad mood.She's got crabby today.
不像你
Unlike you
你为何守了这个秘密五十年
Why did you kept this secret for fifity years?
我的行为是罪过
What I've done was a sin,
所以要隐藏起来
and I kept it all hidden away.
但是我心里想
And then I thought to myself,
把它隐藏起来也是一种罪
kept it all hidden away was also a sin,
因为我欺骗了别人
cos I was lying to everybody.
随着事情发展 我陷入迷思
And as it went on I tied myself up in knots.
到底哪一个更有罪
worring which was worse sin of the two,
生了这个孩子 还是说谎
having the babay,or the lying
到最后我也无法下定论了 马丁
In the end I couldn't make up my mind Martin.
我想问问你 马丁
I was gonna asking you Martin.
你写这篇故事 可不可以不用我的真名
If you'd be possible not to use my real name to write the story
叫我南希还不错
I was good to called me Nancy.
我一直很喜欢这个名字 南希
I was always like this name,Nancy.
我侄女叫南希
My niece is called Nancy
噢 别人不会以为是她吧
oh people might think it's her.
安怎么样
What about Ann?
安·波琳 多好听的名字 噢 也有人用了
Ann Boleyn.It's a lovely name,oh but somebody had that.
我必须写你的真名 菲洛梅娜
I'm going to have to call you by your real name, Philomena.
这是规定
That's the way it works.
玛丽
Mary?
是的
Yes.
我是马丁
I'm Martin
这位是菲洛梅娜 安东尼的母亲
This is Philomena. Anthony's mother.
迈克尔的母亲
Michael's mother.
好吧
Okay
这是我们的母亲
That's our mother.
我是说 养母
I mean,our adopted mother.
她是个漂亮的女人 玛丽 看起来很漂亮
She is a nice lady,Mary.She looks nice.
我不想跟你说谎
I'm not gonna lie to you Philomena,
我们的童年并不愉快
we didn't have the happiest childhood.
玛吉还好
Marge was okay
但是我们的父亲 博士 脾气很坏
but our father, Doc, could be a very hard man.
别再折磨她了
Stop torturing her!
这就是他 和皮特·奥尔森
That's him with Pete Olsson.
迈克和皮特是……
Mike and pete were...
没关系的 玛丽
It's all right Mary,
我知道安东尼是同性恋
I know that Anthony was a gay homosexual.
我们还见过玛茜娅
And we met Marcia
以前帮他打掩护 是吗 马丁
who I believe was his beard, is that right Martin?
是的
Yes,it might be right
一定很糟糕
It must have been terrible,
一辈子藏着这个秘密
having to keep it a secret his whole life.
我觉得我儿子死于艾滋病
I assume my son died from Aids.
是的
Yes.
他最后几年过得很不如意
He wasn'ttoo happy with last couple of years of his life,
为里根工作
working for Reagan
过得很糟糕
It was pretty mess up about him.
共和党削减了艾滋病研究的经费
The Republicans cut funding into Aids research
因为他们把这归咎于同志的生活方式
because they blamed the epidemic on gay lifestyles.
因为他们有些人不愿戴套
Because some of them wouldn't wear condoms
说是影响快感
because they said it spoilt the feeling.
他葬在哪
Where's he buried Mary?
爸爸想让他葬在圣路易斯的家族墓地
Dad wanted him buried in the family plot in St. Louis
但皮特不干
but Pete wouldn't allow it.
大吵了一架
There was a huge fight.
我最后都没去
I didn't go in the end,
不想卷入其中
I didn't want to get involved.
你该去问问皮特
You should talk to Pete about it.
我们有皮特的号码
Yes,we have Pete's number.
回来去拜访他 菲洛梅娜
I think we'll pay a visit to him.Philomena.
玛丽 有件事我一直想问
Mary, can I just ask, there's one thing I'd like to know.
安东尼有没有提起过爱尔兰 或他来自哪里
Did Anthony ever mention Ireland, or where he'd come from?
没有 我们真的不谈论这个
Not really. No.We didn't really talked about that.
不 你为什么
No. Why would you.
要加糖吗
You want some sugar?
如果你不嫌麻烦
If you do not mind.
牛奶?
Some milk?
很好
Nice
谢谢
Thank you very much.
很奇怪
It seems odd,
她和你坐在一起 而你又认识她的生母
She was in the same room,someone knew her mother,
可她却连一句都没问过她
but she asked no questions about her.
这有什么奇怪
Why is that odd?
她只是在回答我这个陌生人的问题而已
She's just been asked questions about someone she didn't know.
如果路上有教堂 我想去忏悔
I'd like to go to confession, if we pass a church on the way here.
为什么想去忏悔
Why do you want to confession?
当然是忏悔我的罪过
To confess my sins of cause
什么罪过
What sins?
该忏悔的是天主教堂
It's the Catholic Church should go to confession.
不是你
not you
天父宽恕我 我有罪
Forgive me Father,I have sins.
我强迫许多年轻女子 违背她们的意愿
I've coerced load of young women against their will,
让她们做牛做马 还卖她们的孩子
used them as slave labor and sold their baby.
我告诉你上帝正在听着
I just tell you God is listening.
我不相信什么上帝
I don't believe in God.
所以 听着 别打雷
So,look,no thunderbolt.
你想证明什么
What's you tryding to prove?
没 只是不需要依赖宗教来获得幸福平衡的生活
Nothing.Just you don't need religion to get a happy and balanced life.
你的生活幸福了 平衡了
You're happy and balanced ,do you?
我是个记者 菲洛梅娜
I'm a journalist.
采访别人
We ask questions,
除了真相什么都不相信
we don't believe in something, just told the truth.
是圣经里写的吗
It was the Bible say,
幸福的人们不去看也不去信
happy of those do not seen and yet believe.
为迷信和愚昧高呼万岁
Hooray for blind faith and ignorance!
那你信仰什么?
And what do you believe in?
窥视别人?
Peeking holes for everyone else?
自作聪明?
Being a smart aleck?
想拍照就随便拍?
Taking photos whenever you like?
那天我在一份讽刺报纸上读了篇有趣的头条
Read a very funny headline in a satirical newspaper the other day,
关于土耳其地震
about the earthquake of Turkey
"上帝又一次比恐怖分子更甚"
God outdoes terrorists yet again
为什么上帝经常有这种需求
Why God feels the need to occasionally
一下子杀光成百上千无辜的人
wipe out hundreds of thousands of innocent people
我真不明白
escapes me.
你应该去里面问问他
You should ask him about that while you're there.
他可能会说"这就是我的神秘所在"
He probably say, I move in mysterious ways.
不 你是个白痴
No,I think you were a fecking eejit
你好
Hello
Oh,hello
莎莉
Hi Sally...
有什么要告诉我的
What have you got for me?
他是个大律师
Okay, well he was a bigshot lawyer
曾经为里根和布什政府工作
in the Reagan and Bush administrations
开玩笑吧 太震惊了
You're kidding.that's amazing!
同时
And at the same time
他是个深柜同志 死于艾滋
he was a closet homosexual who died of Aids.
这放在周末版简直太完美了
This is perfect for the weekend section.
而且 我见过他
and I met him.
你见过他 私人会面吗
You met him? So there's a personal angle?
是的 其中之一
Well yeh, that's one of the angles.
人们需要了解发生了什么
people need to know what happened here
这不公平
it's an injustice.
那些坏修女呢
What about the evil nuns?
还在那 她们又跑不掉
Oh still there, they haven't gone away.
也许变得更加邪恶了
If anything they're a bit more evil.
干得好 马丁 我回来再打给你
It's great Martin .I'll call you back.
说出来 别害怕
Speak out now,dear,don't be afraid.
你必须面对
Have to face,my dear.
上帝会宽恕你
God will forgive you.
菲儿 你说的没错
Phil,you were right,
我是个白痴
I was being a "feckin eejit"
对不起
And I'm sorry
我在里面思考了一下
I was doing some thinking in there.
我要从布莱德福德和比格雷那里贷款
I'm going to get a loan from the Bradford and Bigley
由于我现在没有任何按揭
because I don't have a mortgage now
我还可以延期还这一万英镑
and I can have an extension for ten thousand pounds
我朋友蕾妮就贷过
my friend Rene did that
她为了修暖房
she had a conservatory built.
我不需要暖房
I don't need a conservatory
我要把钱还给你
and I could give you the money
付清所有机票和宾馆的开销
to cover the cost of all the flights and the hotel rooms
你也不会有损失
then you won't be out of pocket and
我的故事也不必发表
you won't have to publish the story
因为我不想发表
because I don't want it published
我永远不想让任何人知道这件事
I don't want anyone to know about this, ever.
你没有任何错
You haven't done anything wrong.
你有权知道你儿子是谁
You are entitled to know who your son was.
你听到玛丽说的话
Well, you heard what Mary said
他从来都没想过我
she said he never gave me a second thought.
他不是我的安东尼
He wasn't my Anthony
他是别人的迈克尔
he was somebody else's Michael.
大概他一想到我就生厌吧
He probably hated the thought of me.
你不明白 菲洛梅娜
You don't know that Philomena.
我应该一直把他留在身边
I should never have let him out of my sight.
我们应该和皮特·奥尔森谈谈
We need to talk to Pete Olssen.
你好
Hello yes,
我想和皮特·奥尔森安排见面
I'm trying to set up a meeting with Peter Olsson.
我打了几次电话
Yes I've called a couple of times
没人回我
but no-one's calls me back.
我一直在碰壁
I feel like I'm hitting a bit of a brick wall.
是的 没错 如果你把他的私人电话号码给我
Yes yes. But if you give me a personal number
不就行了吗
I think it's OK with that.
我知道 但我不明白为何他拒绝见我和菲洛梅娜
Yes,but I don't understand why he refuses me and Philomena
就一小时
for just an hour.
菲洛梅娜 你还好吗
Philomena are you alright?
抱歉 先生 没人接
I'm sorry sir,no answer.
她不可能自己出门
she wouldn't have gone anywhere by herself.
可能没什么
It probably nothing
但她是个年龄很大的爱尔兰人
but she is quite old and Irish.
你是她亲属吗
And she's a relative?
除非亲属 否则不能让您进去
Cos I can't let you in unless she's a relative.
是的 她是我母亲
Yes.She's... my mother.
门房
Concierge
菲儿
Phil?
妈
Mum
有人吗
Hello?
妈
Mum?
原来在这儿
There you are!
怎么回事
What's the matter?
我到处找你
I wondered where you were.
您母亲还好吗
Is your mother okay now?
是的 谢谢
Yes, thanks.
我只能这样说 他才让我进
I had to say that to get him to let me in.
你不该关阳台门
You shouldn't have the balcony door shut
外面敲门就听不见了
if you can't hear the door to the room.
我只是出来哭一会 就这样
I was just out here having a little cry, that's all
好吧
Right.
进屋吧
You need to came inside.
你不会认为我想跳楼吧
You didn't think I was going to jump off the balcony?
当然不会
No of course not.
你和皮特·奥尔森联系上了吗
Did you get through Pete Olsson?
打到他的办公室 他不在
Just his office,he wasn't there.
他只是不想见我
He just don't wanna see me
有些人不愿意面对过去
Some people have problems dealing with the past
而不是针对你
not you though,
我相信他会接受的
I'm sure he'll come around
你的座驾备好了
Your chariot awaits
我把它漆成黄色了
I got it in yellow
马丁 有些事我想跟你说
Martin, there's something I have to say to you
我已经下定决心了
I've made a decision and my mind's made up
你说什么都不会让我改变主意
and there's nothing you can say that's going to make me change it.
我很感激你为我做的一切
I appreciate everything you've done for me,
谢谢你照顾我
and thank you for looking after me,
我享受了高级宾馆和美食 等等一切
I've enjoyed the hotels and all the food and everything,
但这些都不是我想要的
but isn't worked out the way that I wanted it to.
所以我想明天就坐飞机回英国
So, tomorrow I think we should get on an aeroplane and go back to England.
就这样吧 这就是结局
There it is, and that's an end to it.
别说那些有学问的话试图改变我的主意
And don't try to change my mind by saying all clever things,
就因为你上过牛桥 而我没有
just cos you went to Oxbridge and I didn't.
莎莉·米契尔呼叫
Sally Mitchell calling
是牛津
I went to Oxford
牛桥是牛津和剑桥的合成词
Oxbridge is a portmanteau of Oxford and Cambridge,
两个词组合在一起的
that's where two words join together.
我特么...才不在乎呢
I don't give a shi...shiny shoe about that
对我来说都一样
it's all the same to me.
明天我们去见皮特·奥尔森
I think tomorrow we should go and visit Pete Olsson.
你自己去吧 我没准备好
Go on your own,I'm not prepered to go that way
去听别人说我不在乎安东尼
to hear someone else tell me I didn't give two hoots about Anthony,
是我抛弃了他云云
and that I abandoned him and all the rest of it.
这是什么
What's that?
什么 -- 杯子上面
What? -- On the side of the glass.
凯尔特竖琴
It's a Celtic harp.
我要回家 操自个儿的心
So I should go home and mind my own business,
看大卫·爱登堡的节目
and watch David Attenborough on the tv
我会很开心的
and I'll be happy with that.
这又是什么
And what's that?
凯尔特竖琴
A Celtic Harp.
如果他根本不关心自己从哪儿来
Why would someone cared so little about where he came from,
为何还要戴爱尔兰胸针
wear something so Irish?
也许他弹竖琴 他是基佬
Perhaps he played the harp? He was gay.
他不弹竖琴
He didn't play the harp.
就是这了
This is it.
我永远没法给他这样的生活
I couldn't have given him a life like this.
马丁 你看 红色的马自达
Oh look Martin - a little red Mazda.
就是他 皮特·奥尔森
That's him - that's Pete Olssen.
我们现在怎么办
We what do we do now?
门前插一脚
We doorstep him.
什么意思
What's that?
这是下三滥记者的招数
It's that nasty journalists do
对付那些不配合采访的人
when they want to speak to somebody who doesn't want to speak to them.
用不了多久
This shouldn't take long.
皮特·奥尔森
Peter Olssen?
什么事
Yes?
我是马丁·西克史密斯
I'm Martin Sixsmith,
我和菲洛梅娜·李一起来
I'm here with Philomena Lee,
他是你已故的伴侣 迈克尔·赫斯的母亲
the mother of your late partner Michael Hess
我能问你个问题吗
Can I ask you a question?
把你的脚从我门边拿开
Can you get your foot out of my door?
你好
Hello?
先生 再不离开 我就叫警察了
Sir,If you don't leave I'll call the police
对不起 我没帮上什么忙
I'm sorry.I've not been very helpful
没关系 至少你试过了
Never mind, at least you tried.
你要去哪
Where are you going?
等着
Wait here.
从我家门口离开 要不我就
Get off my property or I'll
我只想和你谈谈我儿子
I just want to talk to you about my son.
他被人从我身边带走
He was taken from me.
我再也没见过他
And I've been looking for him ever since.
看到了吗 马丁
Would you look to him Martin
等等
Wait
怎么了 哪里不对
What's what? What's wrong?
他去过爱尔兰
He went to Ireland?
去过罗斯克里
He went to Roscrea?
是的 我带他去的
Yeah,I took him.
他一直在找你 菲洛梅娜
He was looking for you,Philomena.
那个修女 我在罗斯克里见过
That nun, I saw her at Roscrea
希尔德嘉德修女
Sister Hildegard.
她已经非常老了 但绝对就是她
She's very old now but it was definitely her.
她们一直告诉我没找到安东尼
They always told me they didn't know where Anthony was
但是她们告诉我们 没找到你
But they told us that they couldn't find you.
她们说你在他小时候抛弃了他
They said you'd abandoned him as a baby.
她一直在找他儿子
She was looking for him!
她用了一辈子的时间在找他
She's spent her whole life trying to find him.
我没有抛弃我的孩子
I didn't not abandoned my child.
他现在就在那里
He's there now.
什么意思
What do you mean?
我为这个和他爸争执
I had this huge standoff with his father.
他爸想让他葬在美国
He wanted him buried in the US,
但这是您儿子的遗愿
but it was your son's dying wish.
他想回家
He said he wanted to go home.
他葬在罗斯克里
He's buried at Roscrea.
兜了一个大圈子
We've come full circle.
"出发了很久以后
The end of all our exploring
我们又回到起点
will be to arrive where we started,
在那里我们重新认识这个地方"
and know the place for the first time
马丁 说的真好
Oh Martin that's lovely,
你刚刚想出来的
did you just think of that?
不 是TS·艾略特的诗
No, it's TS Eliot.
没关系 依旧很好
Well never mind it's still nice.
可以进去了吗
Shall we go in?
你不会进去大吵大闹吧
You're not going to make a scene in there are you?
我只是问几个问题
I'm just going to ask a few questions.
不喝茶
And I don't want any tea,
也不吃点心
and I don't want any cake.
进来 菲洛梅娜
do come in Philomena.
克莱尔修女请你等她
Sister Claire has asked if you could wait here for her.
记住 马丁 不是她们的错
Now remember Martin, it's not their fault.
她们不知道安东尼还有另一个名字
They didn't know that Anthony had a different name.
有个人知道
One of the did.
你以为你在干什么
Excuse me what do you think you're doing?
你不能来这里
You're not allowed here
他直接就闯进来
He just walked straight in.
这种行为太无礼了
This is completely inappropriate behaviour!
希尔德嘉德修女
Sister Hildegarde.
我不是来伤害你的
I'm not here to hurt you,
只是问你一个问题
I've just come to ask you a question.
我是菲洛梅娜·李的朋友
I'm a friend of Philomena Lee
我在一段视频里见过你和他儿子
I saw you on a video with her son.
你明知他们母子在互相寻找
When you knew they looking for each other,
为什么不告诉真相
why did you keep them apart?
我们要叫警卫了
We're going to call the guards
除非你立即离开
unless you leave immediately.
她不回答我的问题 我就不走
I'm not leaving if she not answer my question.
很抱歉 你整个人的态度
I'm sorry I think your whole manner,
真是令人作呕
it is absolutely disgusting.
我来告诉你什么叫令人作呕
I'll tell you what's disgusting,
对一个垂死之人说谎
lying to a dying man.
你本可以给他们一点点珍贵的时间
You could have given them a few precious moments
让他死前和生母团聚
with his mother before he passed away
但你选择了说谎
but you chose not to.
这才是令人作呕
That's disgusting.
过来 希尔德嘉德修女
Come on Sister Hildegarde,
你不必听这些
you don't have to listen to this.
你不是基督徒吧
Not very Christian is it
等等
Wait!
让我来告诉你
Let me tell you something
我宣誓终身守贞
I have kept my vow of chastity my whole life.
苦修禁欲
Self denial and mortification of the flesh,
这样才能更接近上帝
that's what brings us closer to God.
那些姑娘全是自己的错 怪不得任何人
Those girls have nobody to blame but themselves,
自己无法克制肉欲
and their own carnal incontinence.
希尔德嘉德修女 求求你
Sister Hildegarde - please!
你是说她们有性行为
You mean they had sex?
过去的都已经过去
What's done is done
你还想叫我们怎样
what do you expect us to do about it now?
没什么
Nothing.
都无可挽回
There's nothing to be done
我来这里是为了看我儿子
I've found my son, that's what I came here for.
马丁
Martin.
等一下 我来告诉你该怎么做
Hang on hang on.I'll tell youhat you can do.
说对不起 怎么样
Say sorry. How about that?
道歉
Apologise.
不许再掩盖真相
Stop trying to cover things up
出去清理干净墓前的杂草
Go out there and clear all the weeds and crap off the graves
为那些死在这里的母亲和婴儿
of the mothers and babies who died here.
她们的苦难是为了赎罪
Their suffering was atonement for their sins
其中一个母亲才14岁
One of the mothers was fourteen years old!
马丁 够了
That's enough Martin!
主耶稣基督会审判我
The Lord Jesus Christ will be my judge
不是你
not the likes of you.
真的吗 如果耶稣在这里
Really? Because I think if Jesus was here right now
他会把你从该死的轮椅里扔出来
he'd tip you out of that fucking wheelchair
你永远都爬不起来
and you wouldn't get up and walk.
别说了
Stop it! Stop it!
对不起
I'm sorry,
我不想让他在这里大吵大闹
I didn't want him to come in here like this and make a scene.
你干吗跟他们道歉
Why are you apologizing to them?
安东尼得艾滋快死的时候
Anthony was dying of Aids
她都不告诉他你在哪里
and she still wouldn't tell him about you.
当事人是我 不是你
But it happened to me. Not you.
怎么做是我的事情
And it's up to me what to do about all this.
由我选择
It's my choice.
所以你就打算不了了之
So you're just going to do nothing?
不
No
希尔德嘉德修女
Sister Hildegarde,
我想让你明白
I want you to know that
我原谅你了
I forgive you.
什么 就这么完了
What..? Just like that?
这不是"就这么完了"
It's not "just like that"!
这一步对我来说很艰难
It's hard. It's hard for me
我不想记恨别人
I don't want to hate people.
不想像你那样
I don't want to be like you.
看看你
Look at you.
我很生气
I'm angry!
一定很累吧
It must be exhausting.
克莱尔修女
Sister Claire,
请你带我去看我儿子的墓好吗
would you be kind to take me to my son's grave.
我不会原谅你
Well,I couldn't forgive you
没事 我已经冷静下来了
It's alright.I'm calm down
我想买点东西
I just want to buy something.
他知道我会找到他
He knew I'd find him here.
我不会发表
I'm not going to publish the story.
这是你和他的故事
It's between you and him.
给你一样东西
I got you something.
马丁
Oh Martin.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我刚刚决定了
You know, I'd just decided
归根结底 还是想让你说出这个故事
that I did want you to tell my story after all.
应该让世人明白这里发生过什么
People should know what happened here.
马丁 我刚看完这本书
Oh, Martin, I've just finished that book,
《马鞍和织布机》
"The Saddle and the Loom"
你想读吗
would you like to read it?
你直接讲给我听就好
Why don't you just tell me about it.
有个织布工
Well there's this weaver,
她相当平凡
she's quite plain really,
漂亮但是平凡 -我喜欢平凡的姑娘
pretty but plain. --I like plain girls.
她被告知要整夜工作
and she's told she has to work all through the night to
用上好的丝绸织出一件漂亮的披风
weave  a beautiful cloak of the finest silk
给主人在他的婚礼上穿
for the master in his wedding day.
第二天一早
So in the morning
当她把织好的披风给他看
and she shows him the cloak
问他 先生你觉得怎么样
and asks him what do you think kind sir?
他说道 真美
"it's beautiful
我这一生都没见过更美的了
I've never seen anything more beautiful in my whole life".
可你猜怎么着
But guess what,
他不是在看披风
he's not even looking at the cloak.
而是在看姑娘
He's looking at her
马丁 我根本想不到这结局
Martin! Well, I never saw that coming.
一百万年都想不到
Not in a million years.
马丁·西克史密斯于2009年出版
《菲洛梅娜·李遗失的孩子》
上千被领养的爱尔兰孩子和他们"耻辱"的母亲
仍在寻找彼此
菲洛梅娜·李和子孙住在英格兰南部
她一直去看望儿子在罗斯克里的墓地
马丁·西克史密斯 现为作家和播音员
已出版几本俄罗斯历史书籍
个人原创 严禁剽窃